okay folks uh so we are uh
ready uh I can uh I hope people on Zoom
can hear and
see somebody uh confirm that you can see
or and here y we can both see and here
okay great excellent now you can mute
okay so uh so the lecture we we we
started with this little uh demo from
unitary of their latest humanoid so
those of you who are in class had the
pleasure to watch it in uh in 3D and or
4D well the rest of you got the the the
the version on uh on screen which is
fine so what's the what's the content of
today's lectures so the first lecture
which I always call 2 a the a lecture is
the first hour and this is going to be
about robot kinematics and Dynamics the
second lecture is going to be about
human hands and uh let's see how it goes
in terms of whether I can actually
manage to finish the first lecture in
one hour now what's the problem I'm
trying to
solve okay so whenever we have a robot
like the humanoid we see we have the
following practical issue that we need
to solve which is that uh we have have
to deal with a whole lot of geometry to
understand the kinematics and dynamics
of the robot so uh on this slide what
you see is the basic setup and you'll
understand it better if I once I explain
it so we have a robot here so this is a
robot with some degrees of freedom and
this is just an arm robot arm we can
have humanoid we can have hands whatever
these are all uh catic
mechanisms and there's a coordinate
system s which is at the base of the
robot so think of it as a coordinate
frame which is fixed in the world so
it's at the base of the robot or it
could be in some corner of the room or
whatever then we have a coordinate frame
B which uh you can think of as the body
the coordinate frame on the body and
this is related by a series of
coordinate transformation so we have a
series of joints here because there's a
series of linkages of the robot and uh
and uh that's what we are trying to
understand okay so let me explain this
better with the uh first the terminology
so the terminology is that we have a
space frame
s uh which could be at the base of the
robot it could be a corner of the room
we have a body frame B which is attached
to the some body of Interest so that's
generically some frame which moves and
very often we might consider B to be the
uh the end effector so the end effect of
the robot may be where the frame B is
and all frames are right-handed okay so
this is hopefully stuff you remember
from your physics and math
classes okay now there is a little bit
of mathematical terminology here and uh
I'm going to tell you a little bit about
this in the course of this lecture uh
what I'm going to do here is kind of
this one lecture summary of what is
normally taught in a few weeks in uh for
example ECS 106 the undergraduate
robotics class and some of you know this
material well so you will either get
bored or it'll be a useful revision some
of you have never seen this before in
which case you'll at least know what's
the right
uh set of mathematical tools to look for
this solving this problem you will not
fully understand it from this lecture
because it really is math which should
be done by solving problems and you know
it takes a few weeks to do it properly
but I only can afford to do one lecture
on this
okay uh okay and th this is the the big
picture at the end hopefully you'll
remember this one thing which is we find
a way to characterize the the kinematics
of the robot uh through the product of
exponentials okay so so this is what you
see here you see a whole bunch of e to
the something things okay so there is M
which is the the rest
configuration S1 S2 so on these are what
are called screw axis so the S is for
screw Theta 1 is kind of that uh for
example The Joint angle something like
that okay and uh and that is essentially
telling us how the final frame the frame
of the body is related to the original
frame the S
frame and this is the basic setup so
with this we can do three different a
bunch of different
problems people on the zoom are going to
miss this forward kinematics
forward kinematics refers to uh just the
geometry okay what the configuration of
the the B frame relative to the S frame
corresponding to some set of joint
angles there is forward
Dynamics and forward Dynamics refers to
sort of physics neuton Ian stuff forces
and torqus so there are forces and
torqus which are being applied in the in
by the robot right so there are Motors
at every joint which are applying torqus
and this means that there is some force
and torque at the end affector so for
example if you want to pick up an object
you need to apply enough of a force to
lift up that object and so on right so
that's the forward Dynamics which is
what do I do on my robot what joint
angles do I have what forces do I
apply okay and what's the consequence of
that and then there are inverse
kinematics inverse
Dynamics what do these refer to what is
inverse kinematics I have a certain
desired configuration that I want of the
B frame how do I achieve that what joint
angles do I uh should I choose so that I
get the desired configuration of the of
the B
frame uh the same thing with respect to
forces is the inverse Dynamics problem
so we have a forward version of these
problems kinematics concerned just with
geometry Dynamics concerned with physics
and then there is the inverse version of
the problem and this is all very
classical material I mean this uh the
basic laws of physics for this were all
known by the 19th century in the
robotics Community uh when these
manipulators started to be built I mean
it was 50s and 60s and 70s and 80s and I
mean it was all it has all been worked
out then there have been different kinds
of mathematical formalisms and notations
that people have used uh the mechanical
engineers uh invented something called
the denavit
Arenberg uh notation for specifying uh
these coordinate frames across the
different links uh starting from the
1980s this uh product of
exponentials uh notation which was
originally introduced by Roger Brockett
it comes from Matrix exponentials which
are fairly commonly used in control
theory that has become popular and at
Berkeley we teach even our undergrads
have to learn this so even the
undergraduate Graphics class vision
class graduate Vision class graduate
robotics everywhere we teach people
products of exponential so you may as
well get with the program
okay uh so so okay uh next I want to
point out how we the the Practical sort
of computer science aspects of it every
robot is described using this uh
urdf okay Universal robot description
format and this uh specifi is the the
geometry of the robot and this is done
uh and in addition we also specify the
the the inertial properties like for
example Mass so all the lengths what are
their lengths what are the angles what
are their masses all of that there's a
certain way of specifying this as an XML
file and and and then we can work with
that so simulators know what what to do
okay so so I'm not going to go into how
we uh the specification of a urdf it's
boring but it's all worked out uh what I
want to do is to talk about this product
of exponentials I mean that's the big
idea that we want you
to so I'm going to talk about this
essentially first in purely mathematical
way and then later on we'll see how this
applies to robots but it's really all
about
understanding rigid
body
motions what do I mean by a rigid body
motion a rigid body motion is the body
is rigid what does rigid mean if I take
take two points on an on the
body the distance between them does not
change that's a definition of rigidity
if something is elastic or
stretching then the distance between a
pair of points on the body does not
remain the same okay so we are concerned
with rigid body movements rigid body
motions there are a number of names for
this in different
communities sometimes these are called
ukian transformations
okay because ukian geometry is all about
what properties are preserved under
rigid body motions you can consider a
triangle and you have the notion of two
triangles being congruent what is that
that's really saying that uh if you do a
rigid body motion and they are the same
then the properties are the
same okay so ukian transformation is one
term another term is
isometry so this is a term used by
mathematicians why does is what does
isometry mean ISO means equal metry is
about distance so that means distance is
a preserved which is again the
definition of rigid body motion and I've
stated this mathematically which is you
have some points A and
B you apply this transformation s of a s
of B after the transformation I can find
the distance between them that is s a
minus s b right that's that Norm of S A
minus s b that's the distance
between the transformed versions of a
and the transformed version of B and
that should be same as the original
distance what's the original distance
that's on the right hand side A and B
the distance between them so you take a
minus B and you find the length of that
Vector so that's the definition of a
rigid body motion or a ukian trans or
isometry all of these terms we use
equivalently
uh okay what are examples essentially
the examples are going to turn out to be
rotations and
translations translation is an isometry
is a trivial statement I've got this one
line proof right that if I have some a
some point a the translation means that
it shifted by this Vector T and so a
goes to t+ a b goes to t+ B you find the
difference you find the length of that
it's the same as that of a minus B so
translation is trivially an isometry or
a rigid body motion or a ukian
transformation this is one example there
is another one which is uh rotation but
rotations actually belong to
a a family of Transformations called
orthogonal
Transformations orthogonal
Transformations essentially fall into
two families
rotations and Reflections rotations are
have determinant + one Reflections have
determinant minus one we are going to be
concerned about rotations so these are
determinant plus one so any rigid body
motion can be expressed as an orthogonal
transformation followed by a
translation okay I just have to Define
orthogonal transformation here but think
of it as a rotation or a reflection and
after a while I'll throw away
Reflections and only be concerned with
rotations and uh in linear algebra how
we express this is that there's a matrix
a okay and this is a so-called
orthogonal Matrix if it corresponds to
an orthogonal transformation and then
the translation part is shown by this
plus T
Vector okay what's the definition of an
orthogonal Matrix orthogonal Matrix is
defined as a matrix where every column
is of length one and any two columns are
mutually
perpendicular and we can do this for two
Dimensions we can do this for three
dimensions we can do this for 17
dimensions in two Dimensions essentially
the fact that the each column is of
length one means that you can
characterize it as coine Theta sin Theta
the second column has to be
perpendicular to the first one so
therefore you get that it must be minus
sin Theta cosine Theta so there are two
versions of this and those are shown in
this uh this uh this Matrix here let me
see if my mouse will do so there's a
version here uh which has determinant
plus one and there's a version here
which is determinant minus one the
determinant + one corresponds to a
rotation determinant minus one is a
reflection in future we'll care only
about uh
rotations and this is the Matrix and
another way to understand what this
Matrix does is what happens when you
apply this
Matrix to the vector one Z when you
apply this Matrix to the vector one Z
what's going to happen is that
essentially that will select the first
column so you get cosine Theta sin Theta
and if you apply uh this Matrix to the
vector 01 you'll get the second colum
minus sin Theta cosine Theta so this
corresponds to rotation of by by
again I would do this with lots of
examples if this was the first time you
were seeing these ideas but I hope this
is not the first time okay now we go to
three dimensions so in three dimensions
we are going to have 3x3
matrices uh these are 3x3 orthogonal
matrices so what's the
definition each column is of length
one any two columns are perpendicular to
each other that means that the dot
product of any two columns is zero so
that's a definition of a orthogonal
matrix so this essentially gives you six
constraints so even though this Matrix
pretends that it has nine numbers it's
not in fact nine independent numbers
it's actually only three degrees of
freedom because of the six
constraints
okay and again the model there are there
the rotation version and the reflection
version which corresponds to whether the
determinant is+ one or minus one we care
only about determinant of plus one and
here are some let's take some baby
examples to get a clear intuition okay
the easiest one which is at the top uh
what is this so this is if you confine
your attention to the to the first two
Dimensions the X and Y then what do you
get you get a cosine Theta minus sin
Theta sin Theta cosine Theta what does
that remind you of that's basically your
planer Rotation by Theta right okay
that's just your standard rotation in
the plane and what's happening on the
z-axis nothing that's where that
identity you just have that one in the 3
three position so this is rotation about
the z-axis so this is just the the
natural generalization of rotation in
the plane I added the Z dimmension but I
chose to do do nothing there so that's
my Matrix so that's the Matrix for
rotation by Theta about the zis and
similarly you can construct matrices for
rotations about the xaxis by Theta and
uh similarly for y axis and so on and so
forth okay so this is just simple
intuition how do we parameterize
rotations in
3D okay uh and uh there are like a
zillion different ways uh the original
version was Oiler angles because Oiler
was the mathematician who first sort of
understood rotations properly and so
there are so there's Oiler angles
there's the one that I like the most
intuitive way to think about rotations
to me is you pick there is an axis of
rotation and then there is some amount
of
rotation okay how how do you specify an
axis of rotation um how many degrees of
freedom does the axis have an axis is in
it's in three-dimensional space so you
might think it's a it's three dimension
but no you only care about its direction
so you can think of it as a unit Vector
so therefore the axis is specified by
two numbers because it's a unit Vector
corresponding to the direction of the
axis and then there is an amount of
rotation 30° 50° whatever so therefore
there are three numbers two to specify
the axis and want to specify the amount
of rotation then there is a a technique
called Quan which is the generalization
of complex numbers so in two Dimensions
multiplying by a if you think of your
point as a complex number then
multiplying by by complex numbers of of
modulus one is equivalent to doing a
rotation but in our setting uh we are
concerned with three dimensional space
so the generalization of complex numbers
to three-dimensional space is uh this
concept of querian which was invented by
this Irish mathematician called Hamilton
and the story is he was taking a walk
and then he had this brilliant idea and
he sort of marked it on the stone on a
bridge that he was walking on I don't
know whether it's true or not when I go
to Dublin I will try to find that bridge
uh that's the claim uh and of course the
3X3 Matrix is a representation of of
rotation and for different purposes we
use uh different rot representations
often for a neural network uh you often
want redundancy so actually a 3X3 Matrix
is a pretty good
representation uh but uh if you want to
do smooth interpolation sometimes people
like quarians for that anyway this is
not the time I'll get into that in
detail but just be aware that there are
many ways of representing rotations
okay next now I'm starting to get to
stuff which is going to take us on this
path of exponentials of
something uh so this is the idea of a
cross product so Vector cross product is
something you have learned in physics
but we uh and that's the the top
notation so I'm showing I'm using this
notation
here okay it's the same as this vector
cross
product okay I mean often in physics you
might have used this cross but I'm using
the
symbol that's just a variation and the
definition of cross product okay you've
seen that before and what we can do is
it's a it's a linear operation mul doing
a cross product so therefore it should
be expressible by some kind of matrix
multiplication and that Matrix is what
is shown in the middle here so this
Matrix a hat uh it has the property that
when you
multiply this Matrix a hat with the
vector B so consider what's happening
here this Matrix a hat is multiplying a
vector B I get by just this matrix
multiplication so the this is my Matrix
here I multiply by multiply this with
this Vector B1 B2 B3 and I'm going to
get get this result so 3x3 Matrix
multiplies a column Vector you're going
to get a three you can you're going to
get a 3x1 column vector and that's the
column Vector here and this column
Vector looks the same in fact it is
exactly the same as that column Vector
at the top corresponding to a cross
product so what this says
is you learned about cross products in
high school or wherever and equivalent
way of doing cross product is take the
three entries of this cross this Vector
A1 A2 A3 put them together in this
Matrix in this specific way and then
using that Matrix for multiplication
gives you the same result as taking the
vector cross
product is this clear any question on
this so please interrupt wherever you
have questions okay and this Matrix is a
particular kind of Matrix what's the
property of this Matrix it has zeros on
the diagonal it has some entries above
the diagonal and some entries below the
diagonal but they are negatives of each
other so this is a so-called skew
symmetric
Matrix
skew
symmetric
Matrix which means that a transpose
equals minus a that's the definition of
a SK symmetric Matrix okay so what we
have done is we've taken a vector
converted it into a SK symmetric
Matrix and uh and that SK symmetric
Matrix if you
multiply uh that with the b a vector B
you get the cross product of A and
B okay so far so good now we start to
move to more interesting stuff which is
uh basically I'm going to show that the
exponential of a skew symmetric Matrix
gives you a rotation
Matrix and that this is the right way to
think about rotations they are
exponentials of SK symmetric matrices so
we'll do that first and then there is a
more General version of this which is
the exponential of a of a Twist gives
you a general ukian transformation which
means a rotation plus translation I'll
give you the intuition reasonably
clearly for rotations and for the twist
story I'll be more just waving my hands
and not going into complete details but
hopefully you get the idea okay so let's
uh take this step by step so first of
all uh how do we think of a rotating
body so the equation of motion of a
point on a rotating body so the point is
Q okay that that's the vector
coordinates of the point q and Q dot is
how is that changing in time so it's DQ
upon DT so Q dot of T is Omega cross
product with
Q okay so this is again from your
physics of angular velocities you should
remember this right here Omega Omega is
a vector
and this is the
angular angular velocity vector and the
angular velocity Vector has a direction
which corresponds to the axis of
rotation and its magnitude tells you the
speed of rotation in terms of radians
per second or something like that so
Omega is a vector its direction is the
axis of rotation its magnitude is the
rate of rotation radians per second okay
so Q dot is omega
cross P of T and uh in the last slide we
learned how we can do cross products we
can do cross product by multiplying by
certain matrices and it is the 3X3 SK
symmetric Matrix so that's what I've
done so this Omega hat here is the
Matrix so Omega was a vector but Omega
hat is a 3X3
Matrix and now this
equation Q dot equals Omega hat Q this
guy is a
3X3
Matrix and this is a 3x1
vector and this is also a 3x1
vector okay so now it's a vector matrix
product
which tells us what how what is Q dot Q
dot is the the
change okay so far so good
okay we've just taken the standard
physics stuff we've converted it into a
notation where Vector cross products
have been replaced by matrix
multiplication with SK symmetric
matrices but this is actually a
differential equation because this Q dot
is a function of time and this Q is a
function of time and now we want to
solve this this differential
equation
okay
right okay now uh how I I have to solve
this equation and uh it turns out that
uh let's let's think of something we
know how to solve uh x
dot equals ax
right this is a the simplest equation
that you differential equation that you
can learn and the solution what's the
solution to this differential equation
the solution to this differential
equation is X of T is e to the a x of
Zer jendra yes sorry Cheri can you turn
off the blur on your on your
camera I can turn off the blur on my
camera I don't
know how to do that if you go to the um
video
resom yeah I no no I've now turned it
off just turn
off you have a click blur my background
okay can you just come here and do this
for me thank
you where your
here there you go but yeah so then they
wanted to see the white board so now
they can see it oh okay ah they want to
see the Whiteboard okay just CL thank
you so much okay now how did just close
whatever yeah I mean I mean there there
isn't much substantial on the Whiteboard
just to know because it's everything is
there on the slides really so just in
case you miss something you haven't
missed too much okay uh is that
hopefully that's working okay but so X
of tals e to the a x of0 okay we can
verify that if you take the derivative
of this what are you going to get e the
the derivative is a * e to the at right
and uh you can see that that satisfies
the differential equ
okay and there's an initial condition
that you always need and the initial
condition is that X of0 is given so this
uh this x of T equals x of0 * e to the
exponential of e a t is the standard
thing which you learned in your very
first differential equation class so
what's what do we have
here so what we have is uh now it
something which looks similar except
that we don't have uh we don't have this
these
scalers what we have are vectors and
matrices and it turns out that actually
the whole story still works okay so what
we have here is this expression Q of T
equals e to the Omega hat T Q
of0 and this e to the Omega hat T what
what does that mean right where Omega
hat is a 3X3
Matrix huh it's a it's a it's a tailor
series expansion of of e but it is the
Omega hat is the funny thing here
compared to the a which is a scalar
Omega hat here is a matrix so now you
remember the tailor here is expansion of
of just e to the e to the T right you
know what that is right it is the e to
the Omega hat T where Omega hat is a
matrix is exactly like that but we are
now dealing with matrices so so you get
I what is I I is the identity Matrix the
3X3 identity Matrix what is this the
equivalent of for when we had scalers
the number
one Omega had T Omega had is a 3X3
Matrix previously you would have just
had the number a a * T and so on so the
t is a scalar as that t is standing for
time but the Omega hats here are 3x3
matrices so you have omega hat t^ squ
Omega hat T cubed and how do you have
what does it mean to have a matrix
squared Matrix cubed you just multiply
the matrix by
itself okay so I've skipped some details
here I mean a a mathematician would
probably put me against the wall and
shoot me because all the rigor is
missing but it all works out okay so the
mathematical thought police cannot can
be satisfied
okay okay and then there is some very
cool stuff which happens that if you
take this so you've got a this infinite
series involving all these powers of
this Matrix Omega hat it turns out that
these powers are not they don't give you
different matrices they start to repeat
and if you put together all the odd
terms and you put together all the even
terms you essentially get this uh uh
that this this tailor Series this
infinite series can in fact be
summarized in three terms the identity
plus sin 5 * this s hat Matrix plus 1 -
cosine 5 * this s squ which is basically
a 3X3
Matrix and uh this is beautiful this
formula is called Rodriguez formula and
uh it can be derived by purely geometric
methods and not requiring all this
exponentials mumbo jumbo but the once
you know the exponential mumbo jumbo
this is a super uh clean and simple way
of uh of of doing this okay
uh okay so so now you've understood uh
so so what's the so let's uh go up and
try to look at the big picture so the
the S
hat the S hat is characterizing an
infinite Sim rotation a very small
amount of
rotation now you keep doing this
rotation for a finite amount of time T
and what you get is a full rotation
Matrix r and that full rotation Matrix R
has to be related
to the the the axis of rotation and the
rate of rotation so the axis of rotation
is captured by this s hat Matrix the
amount of rotation is captured by five
which is just your angular velocity in
radians per second if your velocity is2
radians per second and then if I run it
for for 5 seconds what do I get one
radian ver of angle change so this is
rotation by uh by one
radian let me pause here to see if
anyone has any
questions
okay I know I'm going through this very
fast I mean because I'm hoping that most
of you have already seen this but uh the
for people who are seeing it For the
First Time The Magic that you are
supposed
to you know go all thrilled about is is
that we had a uh you we had an infinite
simil amount of rotation which we
capture by the axis of rotation and rate
of rotation that's given by this s hat
and then we rotate by an amount for an
amount of time T and now we get a full
rotation Matrix and that rotation Matrix
is the exponential of five s hat and in
fact there is a fairly nice compact
formula for it
okay so this is and uh okay uh any
questions on this okay let me actually
take a poll here how many people here
have seen this
before okay so 50/50 which is fine okay
that's what I expected now I will uh run
through some basic facts about
isometries which uh are kind of
intuitive which is the comp position of
two isometries is an isometry so an so
this is kind of straightforward right
you just have you do some multiplication
and uh so there's a a rotation Matrix a
and then a translation T and you have
two of these so one is S1 one is S2 you
compose them together you'll get
another uh another isometry I'm using
the term isometry interchangeably with
with ukian Mo motion or it's like a
rigid body movement they're all the
same uh isometries are every isometry
has an inverse meaning that there is an
A and A T and then it does something and
there is the inverse of that meaning
that if you compose uh transform so you
have a isometry a and then there is some
isometry B such that b composed with a
is the identity so you can think about
this right if there's a rotation then
you just do the the opposite okay if
there's a rotation and translation it
turns out there is some rotation and
translation which cancels
it and uh there is an identity element
which is what's the identity element for
isometries the rotation Matrix should be
a identity Matrix the translation Vector
should be a zero Vector okay so that's
the identity uh corresponding to
this okay
uh what I'm doing here is I've now I I I
told you the story for rotations right I
said rotations are easy to think about
exponentials of SK symmetric matrices
that's what rotations are now I'm
getting you ready for the general case
and the general case is that there will
be a rotation and a
translation okay and first I'll have to
figure out how to express that in Matrix
form and then how to convert that to
exponential of something that's what I'm
leading up to so uh so uh first a little
another bit of preparation uh
homogeneous
coordinates homogeneous coordinates are
that when you are in any space these
require having an extra coordinate so if
you are in one dimensional space
normally you use one number in
homogeneous coordinates you use two
numbers when you are in two-dimensional
space normally you need two
numbers but in homogeneous coordinates
you need three numbers and so on so
basically in
any so in N
dimensional space we need n+ one
numbers if you use homogeneous
coordinates okay you might be wondering
why why do we want to do this or first
of all this adds redundancy so how do we
resolve the redundancy so the redundancy
is resolved by this uh this uh
characterization which is that if you
have a a vector of
coordinates right then any scalar
multiple with a
nonzero value of that scalar corresponds
to the same
point so this X1 X2 so on up to xn
Vector corresponds to the same point as
when you take this vector and you have
every component multiplied by Lambda
which is non
zero so basically we added an extra
degree of freedom and then we took away
the degree of
Freedom it sounds stupid it actually
where it delivers value for you is in
dealing with what I called points at
infinity and there's a again a long
story here which is that uh uh for
example perspective transformation which
we study in computer vision these are a
subset of what are called projective
Transformations and with perspective
Transformations you have the phenomena
that parallel lines can meet at a
point okay but
that how do you almost noded but that's
not true right lines which are not
parallel intersect at a point but
parallel lines don't meet at a point so
we have to make a story the story is
that the parallel lines meet at a point
at
infinity and how do you characterize a
point at
Infinity okay in regular ukian
coordinates the cartisian coordinates
that you learned from again in your high
school those don't deal with that but
once you have homogeneous coordinates
then you can allow for points at
Infinity if you make the last component
zero for example but anyway I won't get
into that because this is not a computer
vision class I don't have to teach you
about perspective projection and
projective transformation but this is
kind of a
motivation but uh the short story here
is uh we we go to one Higher
dimensional uh representation but then
we remove that degree of Freedom by
saying that Scala multiples correspond
to the same
Point again look it up on Wikipedia if
you have never seen homogeneous
coordinates
before
okay this now
uh helps us because this now enables us
to
represent uh General ukan motions by a
matrix so the this is the representation
that I'm uh going to talk about so we
are now dealing with with isometries in
three-dimensional space so these consist
of a rotation followed by translation so
in this 4x4 Matrix the the the first
three rows and first three columns what
do they look like since they have the
letter R what do you think they
correspond to some rotation right good
choice yes good guess so this R11 R12
r13 that 3x3 submatrix corresponds to
the rotation part P1 P2 P3 this
corresponds to the translation part okay
and uh you you can see that this is a
4x4 Matrix even though we are dealing
with Transformations which are in
threedimensional
space well what's the what does this 4x4
Matrix want on its right hand side a 4x1
Vector how do I get a 4 by1 Vector when
you
have points in in the threedimensional
space homogeneous coordinates right so
the homogeneous coordinates of a point
and three dimensions are going to be a
four vector and the trivial way of
making homogeneous
coordinates is as follows so suppose I
had
a I had a I don't know just name me some
Vector in threedimensional Space 2 - 3 7
this is a vector in
R3 okay I want to express this in
projective threedimensional space what
do I
do I need to make it a four Vector it's
2 - 3 7
1 just add a one okay so this is a
trivial Way by which we can convert any
any of my usual three-dimensional points
in a threedimensional space into a four
Vector which is what we'll need in this
setup uh so this gives you no additional
value the additional value comes in when
we are dealing with points at Infinity
so points at Infinity you can have
instead of that one you can have a zero
and you can you can essentially consider
points at Infinity but we won't deal
with that here okay and uh and this for
so now there's a little exercise which I
won't take you through which is that if
I take
any point let's call this uh I don't
know let's call this X1 X2
X31 that's my point X1 X2 X3 in
threedimensional space and I'm
converting it to by adding one as the
last component right so now it's a point
in I'm using the same it's the same
point but expressed in homogeneous
coordinates now I can
multiply that 4x4 Matrix uh that we have
in the slide times this Vector X1 X2 X3
1 okay do the algebra and you will find
that this will essentially turn out to
be equivalent of the rotational Matrix R
applied to X1 X2 X3 plus the translation
Vector P1 P2 P3 so this is 4x4 Matrix is
honest to God representation of a
rotation followed by
translation and and this is kind of
tricky to do because we love linear
Transformations we love matrices
but why can't I do a rotation and
translation in as a straightforward
linear
transformation rotation is a linear
transformation but translation is not
see if you just think of translation we
all think linear Transformations are
simple and easy and translation is
simple as easy so therefore translation
must be a linear transformation no
that's not true translation is not a
linear transform
formation right just think about
additivity if you have a point a it
becomes a plus T if you have a point B
it becomes V plus T the sum of a plus
b it becomes a plus B+ T whereas if you
had linearity it would be a plus B+ 2T
so translation is not a linear
transformation okay so we have to go
through some mumo jumbo to make it into
a linear
transformation and it turns out that
going to homo genius coordinates enables
you to do that and in this setup with
this 4x4 Matrix you have both a rotation
and a translation which are Incorporated
nicely okay then this terminology
se3 special ukian group se3 so the three
here stands for okay let's just unpack
these these representation what is the
three the three is because it's three
diens
questions why e it's in honor of uid
ukian movements are rigid body motions
what is s s is special can somebody
guess why what is the s
for the S is because we want to remind
you that the determinant is plus
one okay so it's a determinant plus one
set up so okay so s E3 and so what is SE
e of
two it's a two-dimensional ukian
movements how many degrees of freedom
are there in a two dimensional uh in the
two-dimensional version
se2
somebody so it's three degrees of
freedom because the rotation part has
one degree of freedom and the
translation part has two degrees of
freedom so that's a total of three when
we go to
se3 threedimensional
space then how many degrees of freedom
do you
expect six three for the rotation
part and then three for the translation
part the rotation part it looks like
it's it's uh it has more there are more
numbers there there are nine numbers
here but once you consider the
constraints of orthogonality it reduces
to three so this is a 4x4 Matrix but how
many degrees of freedom does it
have
six
okay now uh now I want you to start to
think of the uh the analogy with the
case of pure
rotations so with pure rotations what
did we get with pure rotations we had a
3X3 Matrix of rotations and this was the
exponential of a skew symmetric
Matrix this
Matrix this uh this 4x4
Matrix we want to think of it as a
exponential of
something right that exponential of
something what are the degrees of
freedom of that
something it should be six right there
could be there must be three
corresponding to the rotation part and
three corresponding to the translation
part so this this is what
we I mean we are going to do some
mathematical mumbo jumbo but at the end
of the day you want to not lose sight of
what it must land up with so that six
dimensional there is a six dimensional
entity which corresponds to an infinite
siml movement a very very small movement
and we call that a twist
twist so twist is going to be a six
vector and this will correspond to three
do for
rotation and three do for
translation and there will be some Black
Magic by which we convert we take an
exponential of this twist and we are
going to get a complete ukian movement a
rotation and a
translation okay does that make
sense because I'll get into stuff now
which will go fast and will probably not
be clear but at least this notion you
can hang on to because it's a proper
generalization of what the story was for
rotations and SK symetric
matrices okay uh let's uh let me just
power through for a little bit and then
I'll give you a break so one is uh these
uh uh this threedimensional ISO
isometries in threedimensional space
they constitute a
group uh which means that there is a
there is an identity you can compose
them together there's an inverse so this
uh this slide uh writes down what is the
inverse and you can verify that right
because you can you can take some some
some point x give it a displacement
RP and then give it the inverse
displacement and you should go back to
X yeah we will which which is why we can
do all this exponential
story okay uh and now uh we have and by
the way all this stuff here I I'm now
I'm stealing slides from this uh Lynch
and Park Book which you can uh you I
think this guy has lectures on they have
lectures on YouTube that you can watch
there's this book you can buy there's
also the book from my colleague Shankar
shastri which is which is has all this
and more so either of these textbooks
cover this in in great detail and if you
really want to understand it read it
from those books I'm giving you the the
the the cartoon version of this whole
story the real thing you should read
those books or take C take
106 I'm curious how many people here
have done 106
okay or the moral equivalent of that in
other universities I don't know whether
everybody does exponentials of twists or
not okay
uh okay I I think this is time for a
break okay let's uh so my lecture 2 a is
going to go on for longer we you uh we
will resume in 10 minutes
but
this of of good old mathematics okay uh
I there is this slide which I think I'm
not going to spend too much time over
because uh it's just telling you that
what displacements or isometries are
used for you can use them to talk about
the relationship between one coordinate
frame and another you can change
reference frames you can think of this
as an operator that you apply on a
vector and you get a new
Vector uh I think let's okay
wait okay yes now we get into what is
called screw
Theory this is very cool this is one of
the elegant results of uh of this area
which goes back to the to the 19th
century and uh I
yeah I I think I'm I'm going to do this
because it's just fun okay it's like
sometimes you have to exercise your your
brain about uh and this one I uh okay
first let me explain it a little bit for
the people in Zoom land and then I'm
going to do the rest on the board so it
turns out that every rigid body motion
so a rigid body Motion in three
dimensional
space that means that there is a
rotation for followed by translation
right this is equivalent to what is
called a screw motion what do I mean by
a screw motion screw motion means the
following there is some line in
space okay this line is called the screw
axis and what the motion the some what
the motion is equivalent to is
moving rotating and moving in the axis
of the screw so what does a what happens
with a screw right when you screw in
something I mean there's a picture here
of a screw what happens is that it it
moves along the axis of the screw there
is a translational movement along the
axis of the screw and there is a
rotational movement right around the
axis of the screw
translation along the axis and then
rotation around the axis both happen and
then a screw has what's called a pitch
the pitch of a screw means how much in
one
rotation one 2
pi rotation how much does the screw
move in terms of actual position of the
tip of the screw so you rotate by 2 pi
then the then the screw moves by a
certain distance in space that is called
the pitch of the screw so the pitch of
the screw refers to how much does the
screw move in so you're screwing in
something into a piece of wood how much
does the tip of the screw move in for
one full rotation of the screw there's a
term for this it's called the pitch of
the screw so it all has to do with the
threads of the screw you can have the
threads very closely spaced in which
case the pitch will be small or the
threads can be spaced further apart in
which case the pitch is
long so you understood the concept of a
screw motion right
the magical result is the following a a
general ukian movement in 3D space which
is some rotation followed by translation
is equivalent to some movement along a
screw
axis okay so first of all as a so this
is not obvious it should not be obvious
if you think it's obvious that means you
haven't got it okay it's not obvious uh
but first let's do the degree of Freedom
Counting
how can you so the AIS of the
screw okay there's a there's a line
around which this screw m is happening
how many degrees of freedom are there
for a line in three-dimensional
space
okay how many degrees of freedom are
there for a line in three dimensional
space okay let's do the baby version
okay I really want you to think because
otherwise that means that if if nobody
is otherwise I would have to assume that
everyone is asleep okay let's start with
the baby version align in two
dimensional space how many degrees of
freedom does a line in two dimensional
space
have no two because there is the slope
of the line and then you can shift the
line so there's two degrees of freedom
for a line in two dimensional space in
threedimensional
space how many degrees of freedom does a
line have
okay so it should be more than two right
obviously if so uh
okay okay let's take a vote let's see if
if you know since we live in a democracy
I want to prove that democracy is in
necessarily the best form of government
so therefore let me count how many
people think that so everybody think
okay I should do the active learning
thing you're allowed to talk to your
neighbor and then discuss for like two
minutes okay
okay and then I'm going to ask you to
vote three four or five okay
okay okay okay so now let's see if
democracy Works how many people think
that a line in R3 has 3 degrees of
freedom how many people think that a
line in R3 has four degrees of
line in R3 has five degrees of
freedom okay so four and five are kind
of close how many people think that an
line in R3 as six degrees of
freedom nobody okay so you are off by
one so so it's four and five right no
words for three know words wor so that's
good now now it's four or five I think I
see that maybe slightly more for four so
maybe I have do have increased faith in
democracy okay so let's think about it
okay how do I think of a line in space
so a line in space has a direction right
so therefore a a direction uh so that
means two degrees of freedom right
because it's a direction can be
specified by a unit
Vector right so that's two and then you
can move the line about in space right
so you might think that that is three
degrees of freedom but no because if you
slide the line up and down that's not
changing the line so therefore there's
only two degrees of freedom so therefore
there are total of four degrees of
freedom so lines have four degrees of
freedom and there is a way to
characterize them called pler
coordinates p n u c k e r and uh Once
Upon a Time everybody in computer vision
used to know these things but uh sadly
in the era of deep learning people have
forgotten all this okay so answer is
four okay and I I'll give you another
intuitive way to think about it okay
this is the the very easy answer so
construct two planes in space okay so
two infinite planes in space then this
line must intersect these planes in
space two points on the top plane two
points on the bottom plane therefore
they 4 degrees of
freom right okay so answer is four okay
now I want to say but now the number of
degrees of freedom with the screw
motion the there's one degree of Freedom
which corresponds to the pitch of the
screw screw because you can have screws
of different pitch how tightly they are
wound up so that so four degrees of
freedom corresponding to where you put
the screw axis and space one degree of
Freedom corresponding to the pitch of
the screw so that takes makes it five
and then there is how much do you turn
the
screw so that makes it
six so a screw motion has 6 degrees of
freedom four corresponding to where you
situate the screw as a
line one corresponding to the pitch of
the screw and one is the amount of
screwing that you do six so at least
there is a sanity check that rotations
and
translations add up uh I mean there
those must have six degrees of freedom
this guy this is a way to specify six
degrees of freedom but now I want to do
the if and only if part any rotation and
translation is equivalent to some scoop
right so that so this not proved but at
least we did a sanitary check if the
degrees of freedom were different then
we know that we were going to be
wrong okay so let me do that but again
as I said this is not really necessary
for this class but I'm having fun so
I'll continue okay now let's do the 2D
version of this problem okay so I I'm
using that to build up notation you know
intuition for this so in 2D you can have
a translation and a rotation right
so there is a rotation about say the
origin so imagine that we
have so uh so in 2D so now I'm going to
do the 2D case so in 2D we can do there
is some origin let's call the 0 0 and
there is some Rotation by Theta
and then there's a translation right so
it has three degrees of
freedom in the 2D case right okay now I
am going to argue to you argue with you
that except in one degenerate
case this rotation followed by a
translation can be converted to t a
rotation about
some new
point so there is some Rotation by Theta
and then there is a translation by some
amount okay so this has three degrees of
freedom this is equivalent
to a new
rotation and uh and that's it that takes
care of both the rotation and the
translation
part okay you can work it out with math
but let me give you an intuition so you
uh let's see how good I can convey that
into your ship so Suppose there is some
object here right can people see this
okay so there is this uh object right
what I'm going to do is I'm going to
rotate it by 90° and I'm going to
translate
it so what did I do I took this object
and let me Mark this point a so you have
some
sense so I took this ellipse
I rotated it by 90° and I moved it kind
of
diagonally right and I'm using this as
just a proxy for you but in general it
should be some arbitrary rotation and
some arbitrary
translation this whole thing is
equivalent to there being some center
around here and then doing it just a
rotation so you can there is some other
point about which you can do this
rotation and it'll work work out and now
the degrees of freedom what are the
degrees of freedom that location of that
point so that's toed off and then
there's the amount of rotation that's
the third degree of
Freedom okay now this is I can leave
this as a little exercise for the reader
but the way I'll give you the a hint to
how to solve it there is what is called
the pole of a of a uh of a rigid uh
displacement the pole of pole is defined
as the point which is left invariant by
the movement so if there is some point
p and then I apply this transformation
which is RP +
T okay and if RP + T is the same as
p RP + t = p
that this is the condition for p being a
pole and can you find a point like this
okay you can just do the math it's I
minus
r uh say if I move this R there I - r p
=
t which means
that uh P
equals i - R inverse T so there is a
point I'm so the special cases when
there is no rotation if you do pure
translation then there is no pole or
actually there's a pole at Infinity but
but if if you have some rotation and
some translation there is a point IUS R
inverse T which in fact does
not does not move as a result of the
eadan displacement it turns out whenever
you have a rotation if you have a pure
rotation is there a pole
yes the center of rotation is that pole
so therefore what you do is you can
take if you if I give you a rotation and
a translation you compute the pole put
the center of rotation there and then
it'll all work out you can do the math I
mean I I leave this as an exercise to
the gentle reader okay so in 2D we can
prove that a rotation followed by
translation is equivalent to a rotation
about some some other point and it's
actually Rotation by the same amount so
if it was 45 degrees it's
45° okay now let's take this idea and
apply it in three-dimensional space and
now I'm going to do a bit of hand waving
so it actually turns out that this
applies that there are people called the
sh uh this is obviously a French name
and there's some Italian fellow called
moi and these people they kind of
independently discovered this idea that
in three dimensions you have this idea
of a screw uh a screw
axis where that means that a rotation
and a translation together can be
converted into into uh into a uh into
this move screw
movement okay I'm not going to prove
this and I'll wave my hands and so but
half the idea should go through so think
of of the translation with respect to
the screw axis you can think of the
translation having a component which is
in the direction of the screw axis and
the translation has a component which is
orthogonal to the screw
axis okay the translation which is in
the direction of the screw axis is easy
to consider right because you can always
you can always do that right use the
screw translation orthogonal to the
screw axis
is essentially a translation in the
plane orthogonal to the screw
axis and in that plane you can basically
think of it as there's a translation and
a
rotation right about that axis so it's
basically get it back to the two-
dimensional
story and a rotation and a translation I
can compress this to an equivalent
rotation by just shifting the axis of
rotation so the axis of rotation here is
the axis of the
screw okay so slightly hand wavy but uh
but the the basic argument is that uh in
three dimensional space we we are
building on the proof for 2D that I did
earlier we can build on that proof and
then that the three-dimensional
translation is broken up into two
components one along the screw axxis one
orthogonal in the plane orthogonal to
the screw axis the plane in the plane
orthogonal to the screw axis you combine
it with the rotation by just shifting
the axis of the screw so it all works
out and don't insist on riger because
I'm I'm just waving my hands you can see
me waving my hands
okay okay so now uh oh okay I I need to
get to my lecture 2B okay so uh so
what's the point so I I anyway I find
when I discover when I learned this fact
like somewhere when I was an
undergraduate I found this really cool
because it's both these facts are kind
of counterintuitive they're very simple
that but you can explain them to a high
school kid I I think that is what what
is pretty about good ideas and
Mathematics is that they are non
counterintuitive and yet you can once
you get it you get it right okay so uh
so now I'm uh basically doing the
obvious stuff so twist so twist is a
mathematical term here so twist here
corresponds to the infinite simal part
of a
ukian displacement so it's like a
angular velocity part which is this
Omega a and then the linear velocity
part which is
VA okay so far so good so the twist is a
six dimensional
Vector okay okay this just ignore
because this is getting into all this
the mathematical theory of how you
transform uh a a Twist Vector in one
frame to another frame okay you have to
use something called an ad joint we are
not going to get into all this if you
want to understand all this take
106 okay and then you can represent a
Twist by matrix this part is kind of
intuitive so I'm now just hand waving my
way through this part is intuitive
because uh what is this this is 4x4
Matrix there is a top left part which
corresponds to
the corresponds to the rotation part and
what is that going to be it's going to
be a q symmetric Matrix and then there
is this V subb Vector which is the
infinite siml Vector of a translation
which is a
velocity so that makes sense right okay
uh and then for screws and twists uh
okay I I gave you the intuition of
screws
you can represent them in various ways
okay so there is an axis of the screw
and I I gave you the intuition right
that that so now essentially uh why did
we bother to do the screw stuff
otherwise we could have had rotations
and translations we wanted to get one
one number which corresponds to the
amount of
movement so I didn't have one number
correspond I had one number
corresponding to the amount of rotation
right
rotation in and that was that map to the
time variable so I have some angular
velocity and then uh some speed of
rotation and then for a certain amount
of time it converts to so many radians
and now in for this General
displacements I have a rotation and a
translation and these are in different
units and blah blah blah but once we
convert this into a screw motion then
you've got one unit right which is
movement along the screw and that
movement along the screw is
simultaneously doing a rotation and a
translation and when you do it for a
finite amount of time like 3 seconds or
whatever after that 3 seconds you've got
the rotation done you've got the
translation done you're all really happy
okay so right is this intuition clear
okay and there's a picture of a screw
and uh and then uh then the
exponentiation mumo jumbo works on top
of this okay so when you apply this
exponentiation exponent of a Twist you
get like a full rotation and a
translation so this works out now the
fancy way of there's a fancy Theory from
which all this comes this comes from
so-called Le group Theory so there's a
Norwegian mathematician called sofas Le
who at the end of the 19th century
developed this idea of of groups which
are also manifolds so a group operation
does not need to be continuous but when
a group is a manifold then you
have that additional structure and when
you have both of these structures you
get uh what's called a Le group and then
the a Lee group when you consider the
so-called tangent space of this manifold
that gives you what's called the Lee
algebra and what we have done here is a
special case of that fancy here
okay I will not get into all of that
just I I'm I'm trying to invoke
Authority so that you are convinced that
what I'm talking about is not
nonsense okay and uh so and we use this
notation uh lowercase se3 uppercase se3
so lower case uppercase se3 is the
special ukan group which is rotations
and translations and then the SE the
lowercase version is the differential
version the infinite siml version where
the rotation part is kind of the Q
symmetric Matrix and so
on and uh you can get the equivalent of
doing the the Rodriguez formula you'll
get the exponential of this guy you
expand it out you get blah blah blah
okay so I I'm not going to do all that
ah this last slide I need to now I need
to say something
which is that uh so so far we were in
the world of uid
geometry I need to get to the world of
neut forces and
torqus because what do your robots do
they move a point in Space the end
effect in space but what's going on
inside inside there are Motors there
motors which are moving these joints
that humanoid you saw earlier it has
motors electrical motors right they move
they rotate okay so what does the
rotating motor give you a torque right
okay what is a torque so essentially we
know about forces torque is kind of the
the counterpart of that for angular
motion and a torque is sometimes also
called a moment and basically this is R
cross F where R is the is the the
position vector and F is the force so R
cross f is the moment and of course
since when it's R cross F you can
imagine converting this to SK symmetric
matrix multiplication blah blah blah so
uh so when we have a so so just like we
have in the ukian world we have uh an
angular velocity and a translational
velocity so here we want to have forces
and torqus or forces and moments and so
this is going to form a six Vector again
right because a forces in the
threedimensional space is a three Vector
similarly for the talk and this combo
the six-dimensional combo is called a
wrench okay so there is a funny paper
funny paper title the paper is not funny
it's from uh Bernie Roth who is one of
the pioneers of this applying all this
to robotics is a which is wrenches and
twists and the title of the paper is
screws and wrenches that you cannot buy
in a W store okay because he was trying
to teach this stuff so uh anyway so
wrench is the the term for the six
Vector which corresponds to a force and
a uh and a moment okay and now when you
take the dot product of these guys so
you take the dot product of a wrench
with a Twist what are you going to get
you're going to get some work mechanical
work right Force dot product with a
displacement gives you work so here it's
going to be the same thing okay and all
this stuff about I mean so the beauty of
this whole screw space theory is that it
gives you a very clean General formalism
you can talk about changing coordinate
frames and all of that comes out very
nicely okay so uh so now let's go back
to our robot okay so there is our robot
this is your ur2 we have ur2 we have
these upstairs by the way on the the for
and now I think all this terminology
should make sense right so what is this
there is the S frame there is the B
frame on the end
effector uh the screw axis for each
joint okay you know know because each
joint is doing a rotation and a
translation so it's equivalent to some
screw
axis and uh yeah I mean now if you read
all the the words on the slide they
should make sense to you
okay and then uh and now when you have
your robot arm the robot arm has a has
these links right it starts from like so
if I consider my arm there is a shoulder
and then there is my uh I think this is
called the humorus and then I have this
these next two bones radius and RNA so
there are some degrees of freedom at
each joint and uh uh what's happening at
each joint I describe by some
exponential of some uh screw motion so
that's what is going on here so right
you get this the original configuration
the base configuration M and then this
product of
exponentials right so because there's
one exponential corresponding to each
joint of the
robot so suddenly this should make sense
okay and uh and then now I'm not
actually giving you all the details but
with this setup the forward kinematics
problem and the forward Dynamics problem
can be solved quite
elegantly okay and often of course for
controlling a robot we need to solve the
inverse kinematics and inverse
Dynamics and uh and again all that stuff
has been worked out so uh this is not an
active research topic we can do this
what's interesting is and we will talk
about this a few lectures down the road
is how does a baby learn its inverse
kinematics because when a child is born
and the child has all this I mean nobody
programs into their neural networks all
these exponentials of screw axes right
the child has to figure out its
kinematics and inverse kinematics by its
own
exploration and in fact the child's body
unlike what of our robots is changing
over time because a child is growing so
therefore all these bones are changing
in their length so therefore the child
has to figure out its own kinematics it
has to figure out its own inverse
kinematics and it has to manage to keep
updating its solution procedures
as as he or she grows and there will be
a lecture a few lectures down which I
where I have which is called the
developmental approach to robotics where
I'll tell you a bit about
that uh and of course uh the mundane
aspects I mean that's what when we have
a robot a robot has a
urdf and uh uh this is a way this is a
format for specifying the the
geometrical and physical properties of a
robot so so we we use this in our
various simulators the simulator should
you use a urdf in the in the simulation
environment
okay so I have 15 minutes so this is
great I can get into the next part of
the talk so I won't give you a break
because I already gave you a break so
I'm starting on my lecture
2 B okay so let's
uh
uh stop
share where do I need to do something to
stop share stop share okay
okay so the now my next lecture which
I've already I'm running behind
okay and then I need to start share
again
okay and
then oh is this probably not displaying
properly in
the is the speaker view yeah
okay ah what am I going to do here okay
let me
uh let me uh stop share and start share
again stop
share
and oh I think I have to probably unplug
this guy let me try again
okay is this good now on Zoom
land
okay no it's not good here Ah that's
good okay everybody happy in Zoom
land okay yes so uh I want to talk about
okay now as I say now to something
totally different so in this class I'm
going to kind of alternate between very
uh sort of engineering robotics type
stuff with very much uh you know humans
and uh and and so forth so I want to
talk about hands now and uh actually
before I I I'm going to just end by
switching to this video but but uh let
me let me talk about where I'm coming
from where I'm coming from is that we
want to understand what humans use their
hands for and there are a few data sets
that we have uh we have constructed in
the computer vision community so I'm
going to link you to a couple of those
one is called the 100 days of hand hands
and this is a lot of video of humans
doing stuff with their hands I think you
should go in there and peruse it because
this gives you a flavor of uh what's all
the variety of stuff we do with our
hands there's another data set called
something
something okay and this is also an
example of what people can do with their
hands and these are little video clips
that people have collected
so what's our eventual goal we need to
have robots do all of this right and uh
but first let's understand how humans do
all this so uh so to to get to
this I uh want
to let's see I'm trying to I want to
play this video but I think it's going
to complain until I have
oh my God I'm back to the same
mess
uh okay uh what I want to do is
uh I I want to play a video which is on
the human hand and uh I'll let me just
play it a little bit so you people can
can see what it is but then you can
watch this yourself at home I think I
don't think you need this from me so I
will uh I will actually kill this
okay and uh okay what we are going to do
is I have a 15 minute video which I
found on YouTube which explains the
anatomy of the human hand instead of I
playing it in class I think you guys can
watch it at home right but what I will
do instead is what I was going to do
next which was talking about some
human
uh I apologize for being not very
organized about
this okay now where is
my zoom window
share
sh then I should
play and then should this
it okay let's see if this
succeeds yes yes okay so this is work
with howy who's sitting in the back row
there and uh
uh uh we'll we'll send you a link of
this video on the human hand which is
sort of one of these Anatomy lectures
from uh you know people who are teaching
medical doctors right so I was going to
play that in class but that's a waste of
my time and your time but instead let me
uh get to this uh slide deck which is
about common Atomic manual actions so uh
what am I going for essentially
I what is our goal what is our research
here we want to be able to have robot
hands do everything that human hands can
do that's our goal this is what's called
dexterous manipulation right the full
dexterity of the human hands that's what
we want to
achieve and then what you see in these
data sets like something something or
100 days of hands is some flavor of the
variety of human
actions what we find when we look at
these videos is that it is overwhelming
the range of things we can do with our
hands is is incredible so I'll just pick
one example I mean I can unbutton my
shirt I can tie my shoelaces I can
thread a needle the list of action that
humans can perform is huge and how can
we hope to get a handle on it it's not
easy what we can do is because actions
can refer to Flying going from here to
Boston that's an action so actions are
at a hierarchy of of scales and uh uh
there isn't so it's an infinite set it's
like sentences in English the infinite
so to make this tractable we will refer
to Atomic actions what do I mean by
atomic action actions which are on the
time scale of like 1
second okay there's a data set called AA
which is atomic visual actions so this
is like AMA Atomic manual actions manual
manual refers to hands so this is from
in your with your
hands what actions can you perform
when you're talking about a duration of
1 second some kind of controller for
that okay so that's the atomic manual
actions common because even under this
umbrella you get lots and lots of weird
cases right and this list will be
infinite so the hope is like something
like a 910 rule that I want to find a
small set of actions which capture 90%
of what we normally do with our hands
and we are talking about here about
hands being used for object manipulation
we also use our hands for communication
I mean when I'm talking to you I'm
moving my hands gesture right
communicative gesture we give people
hugs right so hands are used for
multiple purposes but I right now only
care about hand for the manipulation of
objects that's what we limit ourselves
to and we are going to consider Atomic
actions and we'll consider common
actions because that way I can restrict
the the set to something tractable and
what uh let's see what we get so we can
come up with common English
verbs right these are common English
verbs and essentially you can think the
something something data said at the
same idea you have a verb followed by an
object so insert insert could be you
know your Apple phone adapter insert
could be one Lego Breck into another
Lego Breck so it's the verb insert but
then the there's an object which can
vary or you can have actions which are
which have an object and an indirect
object so I slice an onion with a knife
then there is a knife which is a tool
and the onion which is the
object right so so this is the
philosophy so basically this is like a
list of English verbs and we are trying
to see what are the actions here and uh
let's uh let's uh look at that and how
went and hunted out some videos so
here's an action
pouring okay now I want you to now start
to think like a robotics engineer and
basically ask the question of what is
the degree of Freedom that what are the
degrees of freedom that you need and
what is the sensing that you
need so when you are doing this pouring
task what do you need you need to grasp
the object does tactiles maybe tactile
matters in terms of the sense of getting
a good grasp but as you are pouring the
liquid the weight of the object changes
and you sense that we pour as I'm
pouring from a jug so that's a tactile
haptic
thing humans are very good with their
hands they can weigh judge the weight of
an object is Vision
needed a little bit because you need to
direct the stream I mean I you'll find
some actions where vision is kind of not
really needed it is needed to plan the
action but not actually to execute the
action okay so that's pouring
stirring this one do you need Vision I
don't think you need Vision so
can
be not not not all of them but just %
oftion
can I mean you executing a trajectory
and I'm saying that I mean we are we all
know like I can certainly when I'm
stirring something I can keep on a
conversation and look at something else
so the vision is not necessary Vision
may be necessary to to get your hand to
the right place but vision is not
necessary here
cutting with a knife here I would use
Vision I
think probably wise right
okay uh but I should actually read the
literature and this blind people if they
managed to cook their meals that means
they must find a way of managing without
it
right so you are you because you have a
good proi receptive sense you know where
the parts of your body are so anyway
this is I think I think that this is not
something we can do well with our robots
today tool use is something which is
currently quite deficient in robotics
what people do with tool use is what I
regard as totally cheating which is to
use different grippers for different
tasks I this is I would never do that
right I mean you should have use your
one set of hands and then just use a
knife use a fork use a chopstick I mean
as opposed to uh 30 different tools and
there are papers on that kind of stuff
but that to me is not the real solution
to the problem here's another example
inserting so inserting is kind of
interesting because inserting so in
robotics we talk about position control
and force control so position control is
you you want to take put the object in a
desired position and then force is about
forces right so insertion is a delicate
thing because you you requ want to put
in you care about the position you have
to insert the peg into the hole but the
forces have to be right because if you
don't if you if you if you're are
slightly wrong then you'll be applying
very huge force and then either the
robot or the Lego pieces will get
damaged so you want to have force in the
wrong directions be zero so it's a
combination of a force and position
control problem
screw
unscrew I think you need Vision to
locate the screw and to have a sense of
the size of the screw and so on and I
mean sometime later in the semester
we'll talk about a project here that
thored which was on un twisting objects
and vision was necessary because you
need to plan uh and uh have the location
of the school but when you are actually
untwisting after that you don't need
Vision you probably need Vision to
initiate but not to continue
writing I can certainly write uh blind
this is not a problem uh we can all do
this uh but think about this from a
position and force control point of view
is there anything to observe there what
should be the
force in the direction perpendicular to
the
Whiteboard pretty close to zero because
otherwise you will destroy either the
marker or the Whiteboard yeah is there
argument to that Vision keep
writing progressively more more yeah so
that that yeah so so always a vision
will improve the feedback will improve
the quality of your work but it comes at
a cost because vision is slow in for
humans and for machines whenever you add
Vision in the loop there goes 200
milliseconds because it takes 200
milliseconds like visual recogn which is
quite fast supposedly takes 150
milliseconds so essentially you're
adding this delay always and uh that's
why I'm not such a fan of so many of the
robotic Solutions today where they use
Vision in the loop uh for very fast
actions this is uh this is uh not such a
good idea it's a good idea if you have a
good model so if you can be predictive
then again this 200 milliseconds doesn't
hurt you because you are predicting
because even though there's a 200
millisecond delay that's only if you're
starting from a blank slate if you are
running a predictor then there is invest
200 millisecond
DeLay So we need to have a predict
prediction is necessary to cope with the
with the 200 millisecond delay which is
kind of a feature of
vision wiping and painting these are
again very good examples where
uh Force It's a combination of force and
position control because the force you
applies in the tangential Direction in
the normal Direction you want it to be
zero right and you want to apply just a
little bit of force because that's going
to necessary to
wipe hammering okay this is an example
of tool
use uh drilling another example of tool
use scissors so this is a pretty
delicate operation so think of how we
pick up a scissors and use
it right uh so the the I like scissors
as an example because for decades people
in robotics thought that they had solved
grasping so there was this concept of a
force closure grasp which enables you to
pick up an object you sort of cage the
object and you pick it up you can do
that but that will be of no use to you
in terms of using the scissors picking
up the scissors is not the point you
have to have it in the right Orient
ation to use it so this Hy tells you
that another problem we care about is is
reorientation in the hand because
typically you pick up an object and then
you rearrange it to be in the right uh
configuration so
reorientation is H goes hand in hand
sorry the for the pun uh with tool
use rolling pen okay this is good
uh peeling peeling is
interesting most of these tasks actually
they don't require too much Vision they
require a little bit of vision and you
use Vision in this predictive mode to
deal out deal with not having the 200
millisecond
problem okay breaking bread uh clearly
blind people can do that okay so this is
pull handles and draw
uh rotation so then is a famous video
that you can find on YouTube which is
there was a DARPA robotics challenge
some years ago where they had this Atlas
robot and uh then this culminates and
the robot just falling off because it
couldn't open a door right so uh and I I
want to use this to uh for one of my
favorite uh uh rants which is uh there
are people who argue that oh parallel J
rppers can do everything because you can
use two hands and parallel Jog grippers
and now you can do
everything the point is yes you can do
it sometimes but if you want a robust
solution you really do want a
multifinger
hand and fingers human fingers and we'll
go into this in the next lecture human
fingers are soft and compliant and full
of
Senses handing over
objects okay throw and catch these are
good because these require uh use of
forces obviously right because you want
to impart a certain initial velocity
through the object uh catching is by the
way a great problem for vision because
when you are a suppose you playing
baseball and you're a Fielder you have
to run to where the ball is rather than
where where the ball will be rather than
where it is now so it's a task for
prediction so prediction you will see is
a recurring theme and prediction deals
with time delays and
uh okay stacking blocks okay now it's
getting a
bit uh big up
pces anyway hitting with a bat so I want
to use this as an example to make the
following
Point humans are very good at zero shot
learning but then you need lots and lots
of training to become really good so I
don't play tennis but if I go to the to
the tennis court and somebody hands me a
racket and a ball I can probably play a
legal
serve right why because there transfer
from I hit some other objects with some
other kinds of bats and then we know
something about the physics of balls and
so on and then I have a lot of visual
observations of watching tennis matches
and so on but to get really good that
means that you have to get
good in your own
body I mean that can take decades and I
will never become a federal
right uh pushing sliding okay this is a
an example where generalization is
important so this example is kind of
bizarre because normally when you think
of pushing and sliding you think of
pushing and sliding some object on a
table but this is uh this is on the
floor and it requires B manual and all
that uh pushing is an important example
of what's called nonprehensile
movement so we use the term
prehensile
prehensile refers to grasping so when
you hold an object that's that's
prehensile movements but is everything
that we do so so parallel joger these
are all designed for prehend style
movements but is that all we do with our
hands no when we tap on a keyboard or
when we tap on a piano or when we push
an object these are all
non movements and we need to pay equal
attention to these and not just PR
inside movements and with that I end
I'll let you go okay